Inventory of the Javier Benedet papers
Hoover Institution Archives
Javier Benedet papers
1900-1977
2013C11
Benedet, Javier
22 manuscript boxes, 10 oversize boxes, 1 oversize folder (14.8 linear feet)
Hoover Institution Archives Stanford, California 94305-6010
The Javier Benedet papers contain significant materials relating to the Spanish Civil War and to fundraising efforts in Northern California on behalf of the Republican side in that conflict. The papers also provide documentation on the plight of Republican refugees in the aftermath of the Civil War and on the political life of the Spanish anti-fascist diaspora in France, Mexico, and other countries.
Administrative Information
Access
Collection is open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 2012.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Related Materials
Burnett Bolloten papers, Hoover Institution Archives
Leo Eloesser papers, Hoover Institution Archives
Biographical Note
1904 Born, Siete Iglesias, Valladolid, Spain
1910-1925 Lives in Mexico and is apprenticed as a bullfighter
1925-1969 Works as a waiter in San Francisco, California
1930s-1970s Secretary, Acción Demócrata Española. Active in fundraising on behalf of the Spanish Republic
1969-1985 Works as a bartender in Mill Valley, California
1990 Died
Scope and Content of Collection
The Javier Benedet papers contain significant materials relating to the Spanish Civil War and to fundraising efforts in Northern California on behalf of the Republican side in that conflict. The papers also provide documentation on the plight of Republican refugees in the aftermath of the Civil War and on the political life of the Spanish anti-fascist diaspora in France, Mexico, and other countries. In terms of volume, the Benedet papers presently constitute the second largest collection (after the Burnett Bolloten papers) in the archives pertaining to the Spanish Civil War.
In the 1930s, Benedet was a founding member of Acción Demócrata Española, a political organization based in San Francisco and comprised largely of Spanish expatriates and immigrants. During the civil war that engulfed Spain in 1936-1939, the organization campaigned on behalf of the Spanish Republic and against the rightwing forces headed by Francisco Franco. By means of public appeals, festivals, and concerts, Acción Demócrata Española raised money that was sent to Republican Spain in aid of children affected by the war and, when the conflict was over, on behalf of Spanish refugees in France and elsewhere. Affiliated with the Sociedades Hispanas Aliadas, Acción Demócrata Española participated in the political life of the Spanish emigration in North America, maintaining a general anti-fascist orientation amidst the often bitter divisions among Spanish Republican factions. Its fundraising activities continued into the 1970s.
As secretary of Acción Demócrata Española in San Francisco, Benedet played a key role both within the organization and as its public representative within the Hispanic community of Northern California. The organizational records series includes correspondence, minutes of meetings, and publicity materials used in the fundraising efforts of Acción Demócrata Española. There are a small number of writings by Benedet in the speeches and writings series. In addition to a number of monographs and pamphlets relating to Spanish politics, the large printed matter series contains copies of the many journals and newspapers received by Benedet before, during, and after the Spanish Civil War. These materials reflect a wide spectrum of political thought on the Republican side and include anarchist, socialist, communist, and independent publications. Also included in this series are numerous issues of España libre, the newspaper of the Sociedades Hispanas Confederadas in the United States and a major forum for Spanish Republican opinion after the end of the civil war.
The collection also contains a number of posters relating to the Spanish Civil War and to various fiestas in Northern California organized by Acción Demócrata Española. There is also an original artwork by a child depicting a scene of aerial combat during the civil war.
Arrangement
The collection is organized into 6 series: Organizational records; Speeches and writings; Photographs; Printed matter; Oversize materials; Oversize folder.
Indexing Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the library's online public access catalog.
Spain--History--Civil War, 1936-1939.; Spain--History--Civil War, 1936-1939--Refugees.; Spain--Emigration and immigration.; Spaniards--United States.; Acción Demócrata Española
Collection Contents
- Organizational records, 1932-1976 (Box 1-6)
  Contains correspondence, financial records, minutes of meetings, publicity materials, and reports relating to Acción Demócrata Española and other organizations
  - Comité de Acción Republicana Española, minutes of meetings and printed matter, 1932-1933 (Folder 1: 1)
  - Acción Demócrata Española (Folder 1)
    - Correspondence and financial records, 1942-1968 (Folder 1)
      - General, 1939-1965 (Folder 1)
        - 1939-1942 (Folder 1: 2)
        - 1950-1965 (Folder 1: 3)
      - Eimil, Segundo, 1968 (Folder 1: 4)
      - Eloesser, Leo, 1947-1965 (Folder 1: 5)
    - Fundraising records and publicity materials, 1961-1974 (Folder 1)
      - 1961 (Folder 1: 6)
      - 1963 (Folder 1: 7)
      - 1964 (Folder 1: 8)
      - 1973 (Folder 1: 9)
      - 1974 (Folder 1: 10)
    - Minutes of meetings, 1942-1945 (Folder 2)
      - 1942 (Folder 2: 1)
      - 1943 (Folder 2: 2)
      - 1944-1945 (Folder 2: 3)
    - Correspondence, financial records, and reports, 1939-1976 (Folder 2)
      - 1939-1940 (Folder 2: 4)
      - 1940-1970 (Folder 2: 5)
      - 1940-1973 (Folder 2: 6)
      - 1943 (Folder 2: 7)
      - 1956-1976 (Folder 2: 8)
    - Printed matter, 1946-1972 (Folder 2: 9)
    - Correspondence, financial records, and reports, 1936-1973 (Folder 3)
      - 1936-1938 (Folder 3: 1)
      - 1939-1940 (Folder 3: 2)
      - 1942 (Folder 3: 3)
      - 1944-1945 (Folder 3: 4-5)
      - 1946-1947 (Folder 3: 6)
      - 1949 (Folder 3: 7)
      - 1965-1973 (Folder 3: 8)
  - Sociedades Hispanas Aliadas, 1938-1940 (Folder 3)
    - Minutes, 1938-1939 (Folder 3: 9)
    - Correspondence, 1938-1940 (Folder 3: 10)
    - Minutes, 1937 (Folder 4: 1)
    - Correspondence, 1938-1941 (Folder 4: 2)
  - Acción Demócrata Española, 1937-1968 (Folder 4-6)
    - Brochures, leaflets, newsletters, and programs, 1939-1949 (Folder 4)
      - 1939 (Folder 4: 3)
      - 1943-1949 (Folder 4: 4)
    - Minutes, 1946 (Folder 4: 5)
    - Reports and publicity materials, 1937-1939 (Folder 4: 6)
    - Correspondence, 1939-1968 (Folder 4)
      - 1939-1947 (Folder 4: 7)
      - 1943-1948 (Folder 4: 8)
      - 1946-1948 (Folder 4: 9)
      - 1967-1968 (Folder 4: 10)
    - Financial records, minutes, and reports, 1937-1950 (Folder 5)
      - 1937-1942 (Folder 5: 1)
      - 1938-1946 (Folder 5: 2)
      - 1939-1941 (Folder 5: 3)
      - 1940-1941 (Folder 5: 4)
      - 1947-1950 (Folder 5: 5)
    - Correspondence, 1938-1949 (Folder 5)
      - 1938-1947 (Folder 5: 6)
      - 1941-1946 (Folder 5: 7)
      - 1947-1949 (Folder 5: 8)
    - Leaflets and announcements, 1942-1945 (Folder 6: 1)
    - Correspondence, 1938-1958 (Folder 6)
      - 1938-1958 (Folder 6: 2)
      - 1939-1969 (Folder 6: 3)
      - 1945-1946 (Folder 6: 4)
  - Miscellaneous programs and publicity materials, 1930-1975 (Folder 6: 5-8)
- Speeches and writings, 1929-1960 (Box 6: 9)
  Contains articles and speeches by Javier Benedet
- Photographs, 1940-1974 (Box 7: 1)
- Printed matter, 1900-1977 (Box 7-22)
  Largely relating to the Spanish Civil War and Spanish politics, contains bulletins and newsletters; clippings; monographs; pamphlets; and serial issues
  - Bulletins and newsletters (Folder 7)
    - General, 1937-1962 (Folder 7: 2)
    - Spanish Newsletter, 1951-1960 (Folder 7)
      - 1951-1956 (Folder 7: 3)
      - 1957-1960 (Folder 7: 4)
  - Clippings, 1931-1962 (Folder 7: 5)
  - Monographs, 1904-1977 (Folder 7-11)
    - 1904-1928 (Folder 7: 6-14)
    - 1929-1937 (Folder 8: 1-11)
    - 1937-1940 (Folder 9: 1-12)
    - 1942-1944 (Folder 10: 1-8)
    - 1946-1977 (Folder 11: 1-11)
  - Pamphlets, 1900-1975 (Folder 12-13)
    - 1900-1929 (Folder 12: 1)
    - 1930-1935 (Folder 12: 2)
    - 1936-1937 (Folder 12: 3)
    - 1938-1939 (Folder 12: 4)
    - 1940-1949 (Folder 12: 5)
    - 1950-1952 (Folder 12: 6)
    - 1953-1959 (Folder 13: 1)
    - 1960-1961 (Folder 13: 2)
    - 1962-1964 (Folder 13: 3)
    - 1974-1975 (Folder 13: 4)
  - Serial issues, 1928-1975 (Folder 13-22)
    - General, 1928-1960 (Folder 13)
      - 1928-1933 (Folder 13: 5)
      - 1937-1938 (Folder 13: 6)
      - 1939 (Folder 13: 7)
      - 1942-1956 (Folder 13: 8)
      - 1959-1966 (Folder 13: 9)
    - Acción socialista, 1957-1960 (Folder 13: 10)
    - CÉNIT, 1957-1959 (Folder 13: 11)
    - Claridad, 1929 (Folder 13: 12)
    - Comunismo, 1933-1934 (Folder 14: 1-2)
    - Correspondencia internacional, 1932-1935 (Folder 14: 3)
    - Democracía española, 1938 (Folder 14: 4)
    - Documentos politicos, 1928-1929 (Folder 14: 5-31)
    - España dia a dia, 1939-1940 (Folder 15: 1)
    - España peregrine, 1940 (Folder 15: 2)
    - Estudios, 1932-1937 (Folder 15-16)
      - 1932 (Folder 15: 3)
      - 1933 (Folder 15: 4-5)
      - 1934 (Folder 16: 1-2)
      - 1935 (Folder 16: 3)
      - 1936 (Folder 16: 4)
      - 1937 (Folder 16: 5)
    - Estudios sociales, 1945 (Folder 16: 6-11)
    - Facetas de actualidad, 1938-1940 (Folder 17: 1)
    - Hispano americano, 1954-1961 (Folder 17-20)
      - 1954 (Folder 17: 2-44)
      - 1955 (Folder 18: 1-48)
      - 1956 (Folder 19: 1-37)
      - 1957 (Folder 20: 1-35)
      - 1961 (Folder 20: 36)
    - Ibérica por la libertad, 1960-1962 (Folder 21: 1)
    - Internacional comunista, 1933 (Folder 21: 2)
    - Liberación, 1955-1957 (Folder 21: 3)
    - La Līberecana sīntezo, 1938 (Folder 21: 4)
    - Masses & Mainstream, 1952-1953 (Folder 21: 5)
    - Mundo obrero, 1974-1975 (Folder 21: 6)
    - Nuestra bandera, 1974-1975 (Folder 21: 7)
    - Nuestra España, 1939-1940 (Folder 21: 8)
    - La Protesta, 1929 (Folder 21: 9)
    - Punto crítico, 1972 (Folder 21: 10)
    - Revista blanca, 1930-1933 (Folder 22: 1)
    - Revista universal, 1934-1935 (Folder 22: 2)
    - Tiempos nuevos, 1935-1937 (Folder 22: 3)
    - Tierra y libertad (Mexico), 1956-1960 (Folder 22: 4)
- Oversize materials, 1929-1976 (Box 23-32)
  Contains serial issues, calendars, drawing, musical score, political button, posters and proclamations, and tickets
  - Serial issues, 1929-1975 (Folder 23-31)
    - General, 1929-1964 (Folder 23)
      - 1929-1939 (Folder 23: 1)
      - 1946-1964 (Folder 23: 2)
    - Claridad, 1935-1936 (Folder 23: 3)
    - CNT marítima, 1935-1936 (Folder 23: 4)
    - Crónica, 1938 (Folder 23: 5)
    - España nueva, 1946-1950 (Folder 23: 6)
    - Frente popular, 1938-1939 (Folder 23)
      - 1938 (Folder 23: 7)
      - 1939 (Folder 23: 8)
    - Heraldo de Madrid, 1931 (Folder 24: 1)
    - Izquierda republicana, 1957-1959 (Folder 24: 2)
    - Liberación, 1946 (Folder 24: 3)
    - México antifranquista, 1947-1948 (Folder 24: 4)
    - Nosotros, 1930-1932 (Folder 24: 5)
    - Nuestra época, 1932 (Folder 24: 6)
    - Nueva república, 1955-1958 (Folder 24: 7)
    - Patria, 1938 (Folder 24: 8)
    - Il Proletario, 1936 (Folder 24: 9)
    - Revolución, 1946-1948 (Folder 24: 10)
    - Le socialiste, 1962 (Folder 24: 11)
    - Solidaridad, 1948 (Folder 24: 12)
    - Umbral, 1937 (Folder 24: 13)
    - España libre, 1942-1975 (Folder 25-28)
      - 1942-1950 (Folder 25: 1-95)
      - 1951-1954 (Folder 26: 1-112)
      - 1955-1957 (Folder 27: 1-88)
      - 1958-1975 (Folder 28: 1-79)
    - Adelante, 1954-1959 (Folder 29)
      - 1954-1956 (Folder 29: 1)
      - 1957-1959 (Folder 29: 2)
    - CNT, 1956-1960 (Folder 29: 3)
    - Cultura proletaria, 1938-1953 (Folder 29: 4)
    - España popular, 1946-1948 (Folder 29: 5)
    - Faro, 1937 (Folder 29: 6)
    - La Lucha, 1934 (Folder 29: 7)
    - The Militant, 1952-1957 (Folder 29: 8)
    - Mundo obrero, 1932-1938 (Folder 30)
      - 1932 (Folder 30: 1)
      - 1933 (Folder 30: 2)
      - 1934-1938 (Folder 30: 3)
    - La Nouvelle Espagne antifasciste, 1938 (Folder 30: 4)
    - El Pueblo, 1934-1935 (Folder 30: 5)
    - Renovación, 1934 (Folder 30: 6)
    - El Socialista (Madrid), 1934 (Folder 30: 7)
    - El Socialista (Toulouse), 1958-1961 (Folder 30: 8)
    - Solidaridad obrera (Barcelona), 1932-1938 (Folder 31)
      - 1932-1937 (Folder 31: 1)
      - 1937-1938 (Folder 31: 2)
    - Solidaridad obrera (Mexico City), 1946-1962 (Folder 31: 3)
    - Solidaridad obrera (Paris), 1956-1960 (Folder 31: 4)
    - La Tierra, 1932-1935 (Folder 31: 5)
    - Tierra y libertad (Barcelona), 1937-1938 (Folder 31)
      - 1937-1938 (Folder 31: 6)
      - 1938 (Folder 31: 7)
    - Tierra y libertad (Mexico City), 1945-1956 (Folder 31: 8)
    - Voz de los españoles, 1939 (Folder 31: 9)
    - Voz de Madrid, 1938-1939 (Folder 31: 10)
  - Calendars published by the Sociedades Hispanas Confederadas and Solidaridad Internacional Antifascista, 1939-1948 (Folder 32: 1)
  - Child's drawing depicting a scene from the Spanish Civil War, 1937 (Folder 32: 2)
  - "Himno de la República," musical score transcribed by Felipe Osta, 1939 (Folder 32: 3)
  - Political button with slogan in support of the Abraham Lincoln Brigade, 1937 (Folder 32: 4)
  - Posters and proclamations, 1936-1976 (Folder 32)
    - 1936-1937 (Folder 32: 5)
    - 1938-1950 (Folder 32: 6)
    - 1962-1976 (Folder 32: 7)
  - Tickets for fundraising events sponsored by Acción Demócrata Española and the Veterans of the Abraham Lincoln Brigade, 1948-1965 (Folder 32: 8)
  - Posters, 1937-1943 (Box Oversize folder)
    Contains five posters relating to the Spanish Civil War and a solidarity campaign in Mexico on behalf of Spanish refugees